A Guide to the Papers of Mary Mapes Dodge, 1875-1897
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Mary Mapes Dodge, 1875-1897
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7715
This collection consists of 22 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was deposited in the library by Clifton Waller Barrett on [17 December 1963] 27 October 1964.
Scope and Content Information
These papers of Mary Mape Dodge, 1875-1897, contain one to three page manuscripts or fragments for "A Day in Colorado," "Donald and Dorothy," "The Two Mysteries," "Whose?," "Over the World" and Hans Brinker; or The Silver Skates.
Also, letters to Thomas Niles and William Carey comment on Donald and Dorothy mention royalty payments, the non-illustrated edition, the plates, value of the manuscript, the writing and manuscript preparation, and the possibility of an additional chapter or sequel and hopes for its success.
In other letters Dodge answers queries by Epes Sargent, sends verses for anonymous publication, rejects two manuscripts for St. Nicholas Magazine but will publish a chapter of one, cancels a publication agreement with Roberts Brothers and switches to Century Company, favors ratification of the International Arbitration Treaty, extends an invitation, and gives personal news.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - "A Day in Colorado" n.d., AMsS, 1 p.
  - "Donald and Dorothy" n.d., AMsS, 2 p.
    Small incomplete section
  - "The Two Mysteries" n.d., AMsS, 3 p.
  - "The Two Mysteries" n.d., AMsS, 1 p.
  - "Whose" n.d., AMsS, 2 p.
  - "Over the World" n.d., AMsS, 1 p.
  - [ Hans Brinker; or the Silver Skates] n.d., AMs, 2 p.
  - Incomplete untitled manuscript n.d., AMs, 1 p.
- Letters
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Fred 1875 Nov 9, ALS, 1 p.
    An invitation to a Nov. 15, 1875 [Edwin] Booth theatrical performance in New York. Mentions Will Hopper.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Epes Sargent 1880 Mar 30, ALS, 2 p.
    Answers concerning payment to third party and her poetry.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Epes Sargent 1880 Oct 19, ALS, 2 p.
    Replies she was born in New York city, forty or fifty years before.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Mary Louise Booth 1882 Jan, ALS, 1 p.
    Cover letter for verses sent to the Bazar for anonymous publication.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Thomas Niles 1886 Jan 28, ALS, 2 p.
    Comments re royalty payments and the publication of the non-illustrated edition of Donald and Dorothy.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Mrs. M.P. Ferris 1890 Mar 15, ALS, 3 p.
    Rejects a manuscript, The Schepen's Dream, for publication. Comments on her health and mentions Mrs. Ferris' father-in-law.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Roberts Brothers 1890 Aug 13, ALS, 1 p.
    Acknowledges receipt of royalty payment for Donald and Dorothy.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Thomas Niles 1893 May 29, ALS, 4 p.
    Cancels publication agreement with Roberts Brothers; new publication to be Century Company. Mentions Mr. Scott.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Thomas Niles 1893 Jun 9, ALS, 2 p.
    Requests plates for Donald and Dorothy. Mentions Mr. Scott.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Editors of the Critic1897 Jan 28, ALS, 2 p.
    Favors ratification of the proposed Arbitration Treaty by United States and Great Britain.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Thomas Niles Aug 1, ALS, 2 p.
    Concerns the writing and manuscript preparation of Donald and Dorothy.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Huttonses Sep 29, ANS, 2 p.
    Calling card. Refers to enclosure of page from Jamie's letter and picture. Mentions staying at the Lisbon but preferring a different hotel.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to William Carey Dec 15, ALS, 2 p. w/env
    Cover letter for early manuscript draft pages of Donald and Dorothy. Comments on its illegibility and potential value if she becomes famous.
  - Mary Mapes Dodge to Thomas Niles n.d., ALS, 4 p.
    Reviews and rejects for publication in serial form Toto and His Grandmother by Mrs. Richards in St. Nicholas, but would print a chapter. Mentions her hopes for Donald and Dorothy.